[Music]
[Applause]
oh
[Music]
ah
come on
[Music]
um
you need a health plan that fits you
better get manulife health flex
choose from four health bundles to get
coverage for cancer
heart attack stroke and over 100 other
critical illnesses
build it yourself to get just the right
benefits so you can start to make every
day better in your
own way
[Music]
find healthy that fits you perfectly ask
your insurance advisor about it
[Applause]
[Music]
oh
[Applause]
come on
[Music]
uh
you need a health plan that fits you
better get manulife health flex
choose from four health bundles to get
coverage for cancer
heart attack stroke and over 100 other
critical illnesses
build it yourself to get just the right
benefits so you can start to make every
day better in your own way
[Music]
find healthy that fits you perfectly ask
your insurance advisor about it
[Music]
while waiting for a program to start may
we invite everyone to answer our poll
questions flashed on your screens
right now
[Music]
[Applause]
good afternoon everyone i'm luis manzano
i'm happy to join you once
again in this afternoon's wellness
webinar brought to you
by a leading global life insurance
company manulife
philippines last time i was here was
this was the start of 2021
and now we're halfway through the year
so
new year's resolution did you guys stick
to your diets
success program
achieve the back on minimum financial
goals well if you're going to ask me
well i definitely stuck to my
resolutions
i am now officially married and i'd like
to think that i'm working to be the best
husband
to the best wife
but all jokes aside being healthy and
maintaining our well-being takes a
little more effort
during these uncertain times not in that
more than a year into this pandemic many
of us continue to face challenges
that cause a stress and anxiety but one
of the biggest lessons that we can learn
from this pandemic
is the importance of being healthy both
in mind and in body
because health matters in fact
we have more than 3 000 attendees
so thank you very much and we hope you
have fun now today is a webinar about
caring for your mental and physical
well-being
but before we continue with the program
let's look at the audience pulse for our
poll questions earlier
it is nice to see that our audience
today is very interested in this topic
now for our first question it was which
of these illnesses
are you most fearful of let's see the
results
we have cancer with 56
heart attack with 34 and stroke with 10
percent
so top of that is cancer now all these
illnesses
all these three illnesses actually are
very serious now treatment and
medication
may greatly affect the person physically
mentally and financially
now we will be drawing later on by a
subject matter expert to discuss more
about this
and for our second question how do you
maintain your well-being
during the quarantine let me see taking
the top answer is staying active with 36
followed by actually it's a thai healthy
diet and connecting with others
30 and meditation gets 5
now as the world health organization
expressed the pandemic has gone beyond
affecting physical health alone
mental health is also part of the crisis
and today we have invited someone to
enlighten us about the emerging mental
health issues
coping and making every day better
during a pandemic
he is the chairman of the department of
psychiatry and mental health
in quirino memorial medical center
please welcome dr edgarto
jr thank you so much luis
hi good afternoon and good afternoon to
uh
all who have been attending this
afternoon's health webinar
thank you very much manulife for uh
putting
emphasis on the mental health side
of the impact of this pandemic and i
have entitled my talk reigning in
control of our lives in the pandemic
precisely because what if we put
as a central theme the main thing that
uh we have lost uh as
as a result of the pandemic it is
control of our lives we lost control of
the structures we lost control of
our schedules our boundaries and we lost
control of the predictability
of our lives allow me in the next slide
to show you for example uh what the
social weather stay uh station has
actually shown in their national mobile
phone survey
and as you could see they did a serial
of surveys one in may 2020
in july and then in october and
uh they they segregated the responses
into how people are feeling either great
stress
much stress or those with little or no
as you could see it is the minority of
filipinos
experiencing little or no stress
throughout
may until october as you could see as
well
on the left and in the center most
filipinos
from 89 percent uh in may
to 86 still quite high and still the
majority of
uh filipinos experiencing great
or much stress uh uh in this pandemic
you could just imagine what it would
have been
if they did a survey also in the recent
surge
next slide please now this pandemic has
also been called
the echo pandemic or the parallel
pandemic
and this is on mental health
and the different researches worldwide
and this is not just local
has shown uh based on on what's
happening now and in
in previous economic downturns
number one job loss is associated with a
lot of things
increase in depression anxiety
stress and also it does affect
uh self-esteem which could be lowered
and it also could lead and this is an
important thing and i think this
is happening in our own country
increasing the rates of substance use
disorder
as well as suicide
during the pandemic also adults
particularly in households with job loss
or lower incomes report higher levels of
that stress
53 percent against uh
uh 32 of households without
uh much uh loss of income
also borrowing from existing research
on the different pandemics uh occurring
around the world and both in the past
and
in the current uh kovit 19 pandemic
uh there's major concern
around poor mental health and well-being
particularly
for children and their parents
especially mothers and i'd like to put
emphasis
on that as many are experiencing
challenges
uh in the school closures and the lack
of
child care women with
children especially children below 12
are more likely to report symptoms of
anxiety as well as depressive disorder
than men with children from 49
of women compared to only 40 percent of
men still quite high if mind you
and in general both prior to
as well as during the pandemic study
after
study in different countries uh
for that matter women have reported
higher rates of anxiety and depression
compared to men overall
let's go in the next slide to a local
study
which was reported out in the journal of
affective disorders and this is looking
at the psychological
impact of covid19 pandemic
in the philippines so let's go for the
results
in the next slide in general
we could see that as a total
16 percent of respondents rated
psychological impact of the outbreak
as moderate to severe 16.9 percent glo
practically 17 percent reported moderate
to severe
depression and a higher a little less
than a third
of the population uh studied 28.8
percent
reported moderate to severe anxiety
whereas 13 percent uh reported
moderate to severe stress levels
if we segregate what could be
reported as the risk factors for
developing
more mental health issues being
female as i mentioned study after study
from
china to italy uh to
to other european and and asian
countries and the americas
constantly report that being female at
this time
could be a risk factor of having more
stress
depression and anxiety also being young
of single status students in particular
are impacted on their mental health
those already with specific symptoms
for example if you have had already a
pre-existing
anxiety or already stressed out
from the get-go if you had been recently
imposed
quarantine on account of perhaps
suspicion
of being positive or for our young
children below 18
and those beyond 65 the prolonged home
stay and i'll go back to that in just a
while because
there is also a major implication
both on mental and physical health for
those
on uh both quarantine and uh
social distancing those with
reports of poor physical and mental
health
those with unnecessary worry or concerns
for family members
who um they they are scared that they
may bring in the infection
and those who have been suffering
from discrimination were significantly
associated
with greater psychosocial impact of the
pandemic
and higher levels of stress anxiety and
depression
however on the other hand and this is in
the next slide
i'd like to show that in researches now
in psychiatry and mental health we don't
just look at risk factors
and in this particular study they also
looked
into the protective factors why are some
people less so affected
uh either in their mental health or even
in their physical health by this
pandemic
well those with adequate health
information
having grown up children that they don't
have to
more closely look after having
a perception of good health status and
confidence in doctors abilities because
they uh they have the backing or they
have a good for example
health status or insurance for that
matter
so they don't have to get worried if in
case they
do get ill this is associated
with lesser psychological impact of the
pandemic
as well as lower levels of the stress
anxiety
and depression that we saw in those with
higher risk factors
also practicing good
health and safety protocols like hand
washing
using face masks etc were also
they had a positive impact on the
psychological
health the restriction on social
mobility
to control the pandemic is indeed
stressful
as it prevents face-to-face connections
and
this has become a major issue especially
in our
uh young and uh working people
uh and uh it has prevented
the traditional social interactions
now those who can in fact be able to go
out somehow had lesser of the stress
so it was helpful that they interacted
for example doing face-to-face work
now let's move on to the next uh slide
there is also and something that i need
to highlight is that there is a
generational divide
in how different generations are
responding
uh to this pandemic and this is based on
a harris poll of around 2000
individuals mind you this was done
in march 2020 so this was not yet the
height
of the uh the surges in
infections and in this particular poll
they found out that 77
of adults who are over 65 these are
baby boomers as well as 67
of millennials so you're a millennial if
you were born between 1981
to 1996 said and i quote
they are unlikely to catch
the virus um and this despite
at this point i just updated my data
there have been as of june 6 173
million plus infections and
as much as over 3.7 million
deaths already and we do know this that
in parts of the u.s for example during
the spring break
a lot of kids college students went out
into the beach and the bars
uh uh pushing further the the surges
the baby boomers there's an explanation
for this
those be born between four 1946 and 1964
and those who are older may have
already a lot of experiences
with crises that they have undergone
and their attention is clearly
not so much on themselves but perhaps on
their grandchildren
or their adult kids but for the younger
generation
the millennials in particular they tend
as their way of defending from
uh stressors etc they
tried to stare down on problems
in a 2018 survey by the american
psychological association
they also found that gen z's
these are the younger batches are most
likely of all the generations to report
poor
mental health however there's a silver
lining here because
amongst all these generations it is the
millennials
as well as the gen z's who are more
open to seeking mental health
help so we move on
i wanted to highlight because
we are one of the countries with the
longest
over 370 or 380 plus days
and counting of uh of
of uh isolation and quarantine
what is the consequence of that
according to the journal of uh the
american medical association
psychiatry they found out that
this combination of physical dens
distancing
the economic uh stress brought about by
the downturn
in uh the economy the barriers to
being able either to seek or the
availability of
mental health treatment and the
pervasive
national anxiety on account
of this very scary uh pandemic a once in
a lifetime experience
is the perfect storm for suicide
mortality
and in different countries including
ours we have seen already a rise
in uh suicidality
also specifically for social distancing
and isolation i attended a recent
european uh
convention and they did a meat analysis
they combined a lot of studies to power
up
the uh conclusion to be able to conclude
and they found out and this is quite
interesting
that those two factors social isolation
and uh distancing social distancing
this lack of social connection
heightens the health risks
equivalent to as much as smoking as much
as
three-fourths pack of cigarettes every
day
almost daily so um and this
is borne out by other researchers
because
in fact there is robust evidence that
social isolation
and loneliness significantly
increases the risk for premature
mortality
and the magnitude of the risk may even
exceed
that of many leading health
indicators so it's very important to
mind that because we do
still have our old parents and our very
young kids
who have remained socially distanced
and isolated now i want to move on
on the next slide to something more
positive
and that is what can we do how do we
reign in control during this
crisis next slide please
bottom line is that when we
all talk about uh seeking help or
reigning in control
it has to be on a multi-dimensional
uh point of view or perspective we start
with
ourselves the individual doing self-care
then we mind also the systems were in
where we're in our organizations
our societies uh our clubs if
any our neighborhood or our community
and then the bigger society so that
together we could all heal as one
and inside any of these
uh programs or interventions
necessarily there is uh
it will help to have training for
example
in resilience i'll talk about that in
just a while
stress reduction doing all sorts of
either meditation
simple breathing exercises and
uh emotional awareness which is
something that we
need to actually inculcate within
ourselves
and the different self-care strategies
which i am just about to
talk about in the next slide so how do
we care for ourselves
we could only care if we start out by
trying to understand how we are feeling
about
things so feel free to
feel your feelings and
uh as we experience
that it is also important to
intentionally intentionally look for
and employ deliberately coping
strategies
whatever work before is certainly going
to work
again this is the same way that you
could help
others start off with asking how might
you be feeling about what's happening to
you
what have you tried as your own way of
coping this
empowers them this is reigning in
control
and because of the nature of this
pandemic where we have
constantly ups and downs new surges
new challenges etc we need to perform
uh regular check-ins within ourselves
how
am i feeling now uh what am i doing or
what can
i do to be able to handle the situation
very important because one of the key
factors
early on that they found to be something
that's
uh causing a lot of stress would be all
the news and uh
social media especially if they come
from
unverified unscientific sources so
it's it may be important to take breaks
from that
too or those fro who are working from
home
take breaks also from your digital
gadgets
okay and at the end of the day
uh very important as part of self-care
is gratitude kindness empathy
and the knowledge that uh
the little things that i do are going to
are important and they have meaning for
me
and for the people who are significant
to me
allow me in the next slide just
10 uh tips on how we
can build resilience because after
all we this may not be the last
knock on wood but this may not be the
last challenge or adversity that we
might
face it's important to build resilience
first is making connections
and in as much as we need to cultivate
relationships it is important
as well to be able to
accept help and
also support when we do need it
especially in the context of mental
health also part of that
is supporting others when we have the
means to do so
second is of course self-discovery
and we've had a lot of chances during
this pandemic
to do some self-discovery of our
self-worth knowing what our strengths
are
in this pandemic a lot of us have
learned some new skills
new talents some have even come up with
new hustles
then third in terms of building
resilience
is making sure that we
accept and be able to manage
change because change uh from
our birth has been occurring and we need
to go
and accept and constantly deal with the
changes that we undergo
fourth is keeping things in perspective
we should see the broader picture we are
in fact running a marathon
this isn't a sprint and it's important
that we
focus on just being able to do the step
next step etc so that uh together
we could all finish this marathon
together
then fifth is taking decisive
actions and this would mean adapting a
solution
mindset which is if we are faced with
adversity we look at our options
option a pros and cons option b pros and
cons
what would be my best option and that
leads
us to the sixth which is moving
towards our goals and that would mean
using goal setting techniques
and strategies what would be the best
to do and as you move towards your goals
assess measure where you are look into
your outcomes
do not forget celebrate small
and big victories so that you could
affirm yourself
and talking about affirming we move to
nurturing
ourself self-esteem and by the way
which is probably something important
amongst
us filipinos we're not used to saying
no saying no is actually
nurturing our self-esteem it is
honoring ourselves when we can't do it
it's okay it's okay to say no
so develop our self-assertion
okay which will also redown to better
resilience
and during times of adversity the next
is quite important we need to constantly
maintain
hope as well as positivity
this means that we need to constantly on
our day-to-day
nurture optimism enthusiasm
and visualize our goals
why am i doing what i'm doing and
uh second to the last we need to
nurture our uh take care of ourselves
meaning body our mind
body mind as well as nurturing
our soul and finally it is important
that we see
all these challenges all these
adversities
as surmountable after all
the the world has seen a lot
of other pandemics and here we are we
still survive we now have the vaccines
uh hopefully this gives us more hope
that we can in fact in the very near
future
lick this other uh the kovit 19 vaccine
as well uh uh kovit 19 pandemic as well
so for those who are staying or working
at home
these are some of the mental health tips
on the next slide
first is we need to be able to schedule
and schedule time we have freed up some
commuting time in the morning as well as
in the afternoon
we can very much use that
either as having you know a leisurely
cup of coffee
uh virtually with our colleagues which
we can't do
anymore just to connect with them and
to actually uh uh
cue us that we are starting
our day second is defining
our boundaries because in fact that's
one of the thing that
things that we lost uh our homes
have also become our workplaces and it's
quite
important to define very clearly where's
your workspace
where's your eating space where is your
uh leisure space as well as your
sleeping space
and it's very important not to merge
those
uh it will get confusing uh
and it actually helps the other people
within the household
to cue them that if i'm for example on
my desk on my work desk
that i am doing some work and i am not
to be disturbed
also very closely related to that is
putting structures and by structures
i mean separating the actual work time
as well as our leisure time as well as
our eating time and our sleeping and
waking
up time that's very important and again
as i started off
we talked about reigning in control
this is one way by which we could
put some normalcy in what has happened
to us
and finally if you're working from home
take a break take a digital break
every so often i make sure for example
as i do my
teleconsults after every patient if
even if i had five less than five
minutes
i'd stand up and walk back to my
computer
now moving on there's some so much to
look
forward to and as we look ahead the
pandemic
as we know has both short
and long term implications for mental
health
as well as substance abuse particularly
for those who
are already at risk of either new
or they are exacerbations of already
existing mental health problems based on
history previous pandemics previous
economic downturns
the mental health impact of disasters
will outlast that of the physical
impact this suggests that today's
elevated mental health uh need
will continue over a long time beyond
the uh this particular pandemic
if we are to borrow from what uh the
experience of the sars
pandemic was three years after there
were there were still people suffering
from
the psychological trauma of sars and
that wasn't as bad
uh as as the covid uh pandemic
also the financial crisis that has been
accompanying this pandemic
will have a significant implication also
for mortality due to deaths
of despair which is suicide and we
see that happening already it will
be important to consider how all these
increa increase risk for uh mental
health
and substance use services will likely
be
a long-term uh and it will persist over
that time and even if new cases
and deaths due to the uh uh
corona virus uh subside
there will still be need for more mental
health
services and to end this
i'd like to remind us in this slide
in the new normal resilience is
not the ability to bounce back but
rather the ability to bounce forward
we will not go back to the way things
were
everything is going to be different
going forward
and in this marathon race we will
all cross that finish line with new
thoughts
new feelings and new approaches to the
way we live
our lives so thank you and back to you
luis
thank you very much dr ed that was such
an insightful talk about mental health
if you have questions for dr ed please
feel free to type in your questions in
the q
a box at the bottom of your screen we'll
see more of dr ed later during our q a
session
as dr ed touched on earlier it is very
natural to feel stress
anxiety grief and worry during these
trying times but you know
it's important that we manage these
emotions because it can also lead to
physical health problems
or critical illness according to a
recent study
done by manulife contracting a critical
illness and being a burden belongs to
the top 10 list of what filipinos
worry about to discuss more about common
filipino illnesses
the cost of medical treatment and
maintenance joining us today is the
former president and ceo of makati
medical center
all the way from spain please welcome
miss rose montenegro
[Music]
yeah okay um i'll just put my timer
to make sure that i'm i'm okay yeah um
thank you again for this kind invitation
i've been retired for going on three
years and so it was a
welcome break for me uh if you if you
see i use the term ubilada
which is the spanish term for retired i
like it because it suggests
jubilation joy action as opposed to the
english word
retired which seems to suggest passivity
and that you're just
in a hibernation and isolation i guess
that's one way of using positive
thinking in today's environment right
you you
you choose a word that makes you feel
better okay so health matters indeed
kobe 19 has highlighted that it respects
no
age i think the slide has moved ahead of
me
uh yeah it respects some age no
boundaries because of that
um there is a heightened awareness for
us to
want to stay healthy we want to avoid
getting
copied and not just copied but all the
other comorbidities that normally exist
even during normal times okay
so we have to understand the costs we
have to
understand the the medical costs the
professional costs
which could result in financial ruin and
result in
agreed greater mental health disorder
because of your worry if you don't have
a job and then you get sick
then you have to think of going to the
icu how much are you gonna have to pay
for all of this
so we have to make sure that
we are aware of it and we make informed
decisions okay
so the next one is the presentation path
which is self-evident um
you missed the presentation path but
that's okay so i'll go to the big
picture first
uh i just wanted to share with you the
population of the country
uh even mix between men and women 50 50
okay
uh close to 50 50. the annual population
rate is self-evident life expectancy
the women live longer than men and you
know what
it is universal on
average women outlive men by five years
in all the countries that i researched
on uh
so the question that begs to be asked is
are women causing men to die earlier
that's a thought right okay now i want
you to focus
on the lower portion of the slide the
per capita income because this is very
important
we're only doing 3 850 per annum
which is already a significant
improvement but put in context the us
is 66 000 per annum spain has 42 000
japan is 40 singapore is 65
in the ice below us at 2 2
100 dollars per annum because
the wealth of your nation the per capita
income determines the level of health
care that the government can support you
with
so you have to be brought back to
reality that you cannot expect health
care
of developed countries where
for example i'm in spain everything is
uh we have universal health care it's
free
it's really very very easy if you get
sick and
you don't have to scramble and think of
the costs
but remember a country as rich as the
u.s
has 30 million people who have no
insurance let me repeat that
the population of the us is 328 million
and 30 million of them are uninsured
because americans don't
want universal health care because they
consider it
as socialism i think somebody has to
teach them
that socialism is not communism and
socialism actually works for europe
australia and canada especially where
health care is concerned
so um the country with the highest
longest
the best longevity is japan the
average 80 the men die at 81 versus our
men dying at 71.
women die at 87 versus hours dying at
75. next slide please okay
look at the income distribution the
poverty level in the philippines is
still
16.7 significant improvement
compared to what it was during the
1980s at the height of the marcus
dictatorship
it used to be about 40 to 50 already
the great news is the middle income has
improved before
the middle income the middle class is
now at 40.5 percent
but very disturbing is that there are
only 1.4 percent who belong to the upper
income
that means we haven't really moved so
that if you look at it
the wealth is controlled by a small
group
and it doesn't really trickle down to
the lower income of 58
who are 58 now again to give you
perspective
i've i read an article recently that
said
five the top five richest americans
control the same amount of
have the same amount of money as the
bottom 50 percent of americans
that's a staggering statistic these are
elon musk elon musk uh
bessos jeff bezos you have bill gates
you have zuckerberg and you have warren
buffett the five
their net worth is equal to 50
of the american population which is
close which is over 150 million
so the us is beginning to follow our
trend you know
whereas in the past they the income
disparities were not as great
now you're seeing it and it is very
obvious in health care
next slide please
uh i just wanted to give you examples of
their
types of hospitals you know you have the
public hospitals and you have
government-owned hospitals
it's very important to know which are
the government-owned hospitals
because if you cannot afford the private
hospital
charges then it is good to know that you
should
which hospitals you should approach now
some of the best run
government hospitals i have to say are
nkti
national kidney health institute the
heart center these are two very well-run
hospitals that even look like private
hospitals if you visit them next
um the health care providers this is
very sad
in a country of 111 million filipinos
we only have 40 close to 41 000 doctors
and most of them are concentrated in
metro manila so there is 0.6
doctor for every thousand filipinos
nurses are a bit more at 127 000 or 1.69
nurses
but again these are concentrated in
metro manila and major cities in the
country
we have a lot we have dentists too but
they have independent practices and they
normally are not attached
to hospitals other healthcare providers
are your med decks
who take your blood when you do
laboratory laboratory tests
you arrive decks who do your radiology
all kinds of imaging all kinds of
diagnostics
you have your physiotherapists you have
your occupational therapist
the sad thing is these are the ones who
leave the country because
the salary scale is very low until today
when i first joined makati med in 2009
i was shocked that the nurses were
earning less than the csrs in the call
centers
i used to run for pldt
so they were earning something like 12
000 a month to 15
and whereas the call centers were
already doing anything from 20
to 25 000. so one of the first things i
did
was to increase the salaries of the
nurses we entrust our lives to them
and yet we don't want to pay them well
okay more importantly
we see the nurses the most the doctors
will come in and out
once in a while when you're confined or
it would be
they'll send their residents not
necessarily them
but the nurses are the ones who are with
you every step of the way when you're
confined
next please
and then you have as oh i'm sorry i you
have informal caregivers there are
bularios
you know when you're sick you'll do it
you'll go anywhere you'll do anything in
order
to to regain your health next slide
please
um
okay you forgot
okay i'm sorry but i think the
the sequence of my my slide
has been changed okay so you're talking
about the top seven causes of morbidity
in the philippines it's cardiac arrest
and cancer
and um that does deals with what you
said in your survey today cancer is
really growing
the highest the the most vicious cancer
is lung cancer because it affects men
and women
and there are two types the the ones
from smokers
and the ones who get cancer from passive
smoking
next slide please
okay uh whoever
branded my slides to be manulife managed
to rearrange it but never mind
uh as dr el tolentino a friend of mine
from pldt
from makati med said resiliency so i
will be
resilient as i said higher health
consciousness will go with 19 now
and what you have to remember is that
the existing
life goes on and so do the existing
diseases
the threat to one's life continues just
because they're so big doesn't mean
you're not gonna have a heart attack
okay anxieties and fears about not just
getting
sick are there but also about how do i
pay for the expenses
next slide please
these are the what are available to you
you are all very young so you don't have
senior citizen discounts yet but you
have
some people with disabilities also get
the 20 discount okay
phil health which is a government
insurance system pays
for about 10 of your health care costs
that's because remember again we're a
poor country your per capita is 3850
you cannot expect your government
insurance system to fund everything
uh phil health most mostly supports
inpatient but now they've come up with
new outpatient
um subsidies for dialysis chemotherapy
radiation therapy endoscopy
and even cancer next slide please
hmos they're about 28 28 serious players
in the country and i understand
uh money life is a health insurance
product
which somebody else will be talking
about in a bit
but what is interesting is the top five
hmos control 85 percent of the volume
if it is not a complex case and you have
hmo coverage
it will cover 100 after you have your
field health
and after you have your senior citizen
discount or disability discount they
will
they will cover 100 so be very very
savvy about choosing your healthcare
provider corporates give
healthcare as a benefit but it is based
on rank they are self-insured
which makes it very expensive and that's
why companies like pldt are trying to
move away for being
from being self-insured because of the
costs
but then the rest will be personal and
out-of-pocket expenses when you have a
serious
case that's complex critical and you
have existing vulnerabilities
next slide please
uh discounts that was the favorite word
that was given to me when i was in
makati med
um the hospital i would hardly get
discounts except for the poor
i would always tell the patients to ask
the discounts from the doctors
because the doctors don't have fixed
costs except for their clinics whereas
a hospital has huge operating costs pcso
the philippine charity sweepstakes
office used to give a lot of
support but of late with changes in
government
they they've stopped giving in the past
we would they would give a hundred
thousand
support just like that and they had a
psc
pcso clinic pcso
desk in mahatma so you didn't have to go
to pcso unless it was for a higher
amount
they would even give the highest i ever
saw was 500 000 i checked with the cfo
of makatima today and they said pcso has
really been
dampening any any of these uh assistants
and it's you have to go through hopes
and hurdles
in order to get any support from the
pcso
foundations of major corporations also
provide uh
medical assistance but it really depends
on who you know
and how you're affiliated with that
particular foundation
lately crowdsourcing is also becoming
popular you go to the fa
to facebook and say you know you need to
raise funds for a certain
person who is seriously and critically
ill but has no
does not have enough finances next
please
this is just for your information you
can read it okay the types of
confinement
inpatient in the philippines is still an
average of four and a half days
to let you know in developed countries
it's only two to three days
with exceptions of course for very
serious and complex cases
but what i want you to learn if there's
any take takeaway that you get from my
presentation is that don't be ashamed to
ask your doctor
for the price upfront for some reason in
this country
we're ashamed to ask doctors how much is
it gonna cost doc
if you're gonna operate on me it is
imperative that you ask for the cost so
there are no surprises
it is also imperative that you go to the
hospital and ask them for
an estimate for the procedure that
you're about to have
that way there are no unpleasant
surprises and that you can prepare
you can prepare for the for the expenses
the other uh thing i want you to
understand is in the philippines
unfortunately many of our doctors still
say generics are not as good
as bran did that's not true the
definition of a generic drug
drug is a drug whose patent has been
has expired so major
pharmaceutical companies spend a lot of
money on research and development come
up with a very good product
for example viagra but when the patent
expires
all the other pharma companies can begin
compounding that particular medication
and it is as effective as a matter of
fact in spain
when you go to a doctor here they will
give you the generic first
and then you only get the branded when
the generic is not available
very different mindset in the
philippines they always put the branded
and they would say oh it's not as
effective
don't believe that they it is equally as
farmer prices in the philippines are
also one of the highest in the world
and that's because their cost of sales
is high because they do a lot of things
for doctors
which i shall not get into great detail
because that is very contentious
okay you should also go to standalone
diagnostic centers for your lab and your
radiology and this is coming from
someone who managed the hospital
they have the same machines as we do for
laboratory they use
about or roche they use exactly the same
things as we do
unfortunately if you're an inpatient it
is hospital policy
to only use the lab results and the
radiology results
coming from our in-house because they
say that's the best way to protect
the quality but if you look at if you do
a
research the medical equipment use are
the same
and they also have pathologies next
slide please
costings i just want that you can read
this it shows you
what phil health is already supporting
if you have a heart bypass i noticed
that
heart attacks are a big source of
worry for a number of you guys you if
you have a
bypass still health will give 500
thousand to cover that
strangely for angioplasty which means
they put stents
which is the first step before you have
a bypass they only give 30.
i was trying very hard to convince field
health that they should match
what they're doing with the heart bypass
so if it's 400 000 for angioplasty where
you have stents
because you have clogged arteries they
should pay 200
i didn't quite succeed because i left
two years later
so this one is self-evident
next slide please
i wanted to give cancer as an example go
ahead since we're
running out of time when when i first
was trying to understand cancer which is
of your consent of your concern
surgeries you cut
in layman's terms radiation if you burn
kimono poison
that was how it was explained to me by
our head of regeneration
our head of radiology in mahatma and he
says you do a combination of the three
and it's no longer sequential normally
they want to
shrink here two more so that when they
do surgery
the wound the opening is not so big and
it is easier to close
also note that 13 out of 100 filipino
males will have cancer if they reach 75
years old
i think that was a typo i think it's
even 65.
people are getting cancer at a younger
age nowadays and it is projected to
increase annually
the cancer rate is projected to increase
annually at the rate of seven percent
next just to give you an idea
in asia it's really lung cancer for the
men because of the smoking and but for
the women it's number three
and stomach cancer and liver because of
the drinking so it's lifestyle related
next uh there are some misconceptions
historically
hospitals were run by charitable
institutions they are what
is considered the best gift of the
catholic church to the world
they operate in all the hospitals and
that's why there is this bias in the
country
that hey why am i going to pay so much
for my health care you know it should be
free or i should be given a big big
discount
culturally we always have this
impression that i'm already sick and
you're talking to me about money
excuse me don't you have any empathy
right so i noticed when i was in academy
if the patient was sick he will say i
will pay for anything
when the patient is recovered suddenly
they're questioning all the costs
and that is why you should ask up front
how much is it going to cost
patients demand the best care and that's
why they run to makati med saint lou
medical city but
they don't realize that there's a
premium for example
if you want the best car and you want to
buy mercedes-benz
you will not be paying the cost of a
of what of a of a kia
of a kia pride right you have to
understand
anything that is the best requires a
premium not to mention that our doctors
study anywhere from for 14 to 16 years
to become specialists
and they keep on studying in order to
keep up with scientific and
technological developments
and that is why they have to recover
their costs because the doctors
at the end of the day are independent
entrepreneurs
they're not employees of the hospitals
um
hospitals are business corporations
we're here to make money
and we are highly regulated our margins
are very thin
eight percent to 15 if you're lucky when
i joined makati med it was doing around
four
ten percent of the beds are also
allocated for charity you cannot
give it to anybody else except charity
aside from that
you have the senior citizen and the dpw
discounts
which are shouldered by the hospitals
and the pharmaceutical companies it is
we do not get any tax credits or support
from the philippine government okay uh
next slide please
latest medical equipment are also very
expensive and with technology exploding
what used to be something that you could
depreciate over a period of ten years
it's probably only five years if you're
lucky
it's now gone down to even three uh
doctor's fees as i said or pf
is commonly referred to are account for
at least 40 to 50 percent of your
hospital bill
um so it's not the hospital charging you
the entire if you're being charged a
hundred thousand
remember 40 000 and that or 50 will go
to the doctors
and and understand that they also
deserve it because they have studied so
long to become specialists
and subject matter experts unfortunately
the philippines follows the us model
of health care we go to specialists
right away instead of going to family
to family practitioners or general gps
in europe in australia in canada you go
to a gp first and
he will determine whether you need a
specialist and a specialist
often he says by definition will cost a
lot more than a gp
and a gp is trained to know which
specialist
you should be referred to um also people
like to go to the er
in makati med we did a study only 20 of
the cases are two er cases
patients go to the er because doctors
clinics are closed
at night and they pay a premium of 30
now we cannot also turn them down
because that is required by law we have
to stabilize them
and they are a great source of bad debts
when i joined makati med
we had 500 million in bad debts because
of the er next time please
uh changing landscape so what are you
going to do how are you going to stay
healthy alive live longer
next the traditional model is you go to
the hospital because you're already sick
then the interim model was you go to the
malls where you have standalone
diagnostic centers so you can reduce the
costs
because traditional models like makati
net had
19 specialties 44 sub specialties and
sub sub specialties here
so you're supporting all of this and
sometimes you buy medical equipment
that will not give you any return but
you need it in order
to retain your image of this
top-notch hospital the new mindset is
please help me
to remain please help me manage my my
health please help me
to be healthy next please
so the harvard study this is very
interesting they said what are the
reasons for
longevity first is genetics
uh in other words it's the law lack of
the draw
you cannot choose who your parents are
but only that only accounts
for 40 okay the next should be the
lifestyle you have a healthy diet you
exercise
you have a healthy body weight you have
moderate alcohol intake and you
you don't smoke and make sure you're not
in a place where people are smoking
because passive smoking can also cause
lung cancer
be very aware of that but most
importantly you need family
friends and community dr ed tolentino
touched on that
these are some of the things that help
you
prevent you from being lonely from
feeling isolated from getting depressed
having family friends community i like
the way they call it in spain when they
say
we don't do charity we do solidarity
we are one with you i'm not giving it to
you because i'm wealthy
i'm giving it to you because i feel for
you and we are one community
that's a wonderful mindset which i hope
the philippines will adopt
next please now the more recent studies
show
that sleep is very important the average
person needs seven to nine hours of
sleep a day
unfortunately majority of filipinos or
majority of people don't sleep that long
and what happens is you have what you
call sleep there
in short
hours you have to pick up the four hours
that you did not
have and and that can affect your
chemical imbalance of your brain
if you're not sleeping properly and
stress um
i'm revealing my age but during my
generation
stress was not a popular word you did
what your parents told you
and if you disagreed tough you just
followed it nowadays i notice everybody
gets stressed
kids because you know i had very young
nurses and i also run
call centers with pldt it's always oh
i'm so stressed i'm so stressed
i think if you say it often enough it
becomes a reality
i think you should develop a mindset of
positivity and say you know
i can do this it's not gonna stress me
i'm not gonna allow it
okay next
and of course you need some financial
stability you can have all of the above
but if you don't
if you're worried where the next meal is
coming from
then you really have a major problem
right you can be healthy for all
intensive you can have a healthy diet
but if you don't know
if you're going to have a job tomorrow
which is happening now with kobe
then that is the real cause of stress
okay
next uh just some parts
parting thoughts safer than unexpected
okay and health care is not
free remember that not in our country
anyway because we do not
while we have universal health care our
government can only afford
to subsidize up to 10 of our health
bills
okay next adopt a prevention instead of
treatment attitude
live healthy follow the hard work
recommendations
health is true wealth not economizing it
i'm very surprised
at people asking me for discounts
complaining about the cost of their
health
health bills and then i see them they're
they're using louis vuitton original
bags you know
and i'm wondering why are you buying all
of these expensive brand names and yet
when it comes to your health care
you want to make it you want to make
tawa you want to get the lowest cost
there's a disconnect there that
seriously has to be addressed
next research the credentials of your
doctors
so that you understand why he's charging
you what he's charging you
major hospitals have websites that will
show you what the credentials of your
doctors
are and therefore you can make an
informed decision
but resist over shopping i had a friend
who went to six doctors and she ended up
more confused she didn't know what to do
some said operate some said don't
operate
so in the end she was asking me what am
i gonna do that's what happens when you
over shop
that's why credentials are important you
will trust the one with the best
credentials
and the most cases handled because in
healthcare
experience matters really and truly
research on your medical issues so that
you're in control of your
destiny uh gone are the days where it's
the doctor who will tell you what you
should do you have to understand if you
if you're a cancer patient and you don't
want any more treatment because there's
no quality of life
that choice should be yours you should
make an informed choice but you are in
control of your destiny
next please this is the temptation of
also becoming
an internet expert or what i like to say
stop worshiping at the altar of the
internet
go to legitimate sources and my
my son-in-law has a very nice rule of
thumb if you don't pay for your news
then you get crap okay if you just get
your news for free
then you don't get valid legitimate
journalism
so the same don't worship at the altar
of the internet
you go and research with mayo websites
you know the websites of major hospitals
in order to make an informed decision
next
uh i wanted to practice aristotle's
concept of the golden mean defined us
it is the happy medium between next
reveal show all of it already it is the
happy medium between excess
and between deficiency so go and stay
the middle ground
except excess of courage is recklessness
you don't mind if you get killed or you
get shot you don't take precautions
the deficiency of courage is your coward
you let everybody else fight the battles
but you stay home because you're afraid
so always remember in anything you do
especially in your work
always remember aristotle's
rule the golden mean because it makes
for i practice it
all my life all my career and it has
helped me retain my sanity going through
five industries
yeah next so last
cheers to a long healthy and i wanted to
add because vikki bello is one of our
guests and vic is a friend of mine
long healthy and beautiful life with a
lot of help
from vicki bellow and most importantly a
joyful life
aspire for joy which is more spiritual
in nature
rather than happiness which is an
emotion that is a transaction
at the moment oh i got a brand new
mercedes-benz i'm happy
but joy is a more long-lasting
concept that gives you serenity and
equine
equanimity thank you thank you for your
time
thank you very much miss rose for
showing us that prevention is really
better than cure again folks if you have
any questions for ms rose all you have
to do
is type your questions in our q a box at
the bottom of your screen and we'll see
mrs rose once again
in our q a session now that we've heard
from our two speakers talk about caring
for our physical and mental well-being
our next segment will discuss how an
insurance plan can help us be
financially prepared and secured in case
health problems do happen now i'm very
excited to hear this because when we
talk about living healthy
most of the time you only think about
working out meditation the eating right
but
being prepared with a health insurance
plan should also be part of a health
journey to tell us more about this we
have one of the top insurance advisors
of manulife philippines
mr kevin t
[Music]
hi kevin yes go ahead bro take it away
all right uh thank you luis i'm really
honored to be part of today's webinar
and share the stage with our special
guests
even for just five minutes i've learned
a lot from our speakers
aside from the physical effects caused
by critical illness
financial incapacity to treat it is also
a huge stressor
which takes us back to our mental
well-being as touched on earlier
and based on a manual study eighty
percent of filipinos believe that the
cost of treating critical illness
is higher than what they can afford so
it's good to have a ready fund
as early as now for our health care
needs because our savings may not always
be enough
and we can never tell what illness will
strike at
money life we offer different kinds of
flexible and affordable health insurance
plans
one of which is our health flex plan now
health flex is an affordable health
insurance plan that lets you choose
and pay only for the health coverage you
need for only 42 passes a day
this plan can give you protection from
over
100 plus critical illnesses including
the ones miss rose mentioned earlier
cancer heart attack and stroke this is
guaranteed protection up to age
100. it's inclusive too
even the elderly where people age 70 can
get this plan
and live in comfort knowing that they
are covered from critical illnesses
this plan can also be can also be gender
specific illnesses
another nice thing about this plan is
that you can receive a monthly cash
allowance benefit
for 24 months to help you with your
finances
while you're being treated for it for a
diagnosed advanced critical illness
you can use this medicine and therapy or
even additional spending money while you
recover
and are not able to work and lastly
a first of its kind in the market or
after your first claim
your coverage will reset to 100 after
after a year giving you another full
health coverage
this is through an early stage critical
illness benefit
all right now there are four bundles you
can choose from but i'd like to focus on
our three ci plus bundle for now
healthplex 3ci plus covers the top 3
critical illnesses that filipinos fear
for themselves
and for their loved ones which are
cancer heart attack
and stroke you can build a stronger
protection coverage on top of these when
you add life-saving benefits like
waiver of premium early stage critical
illness
recovery benefit second advanced
critical illness claim benefit
child critical illness benefit male
cancer or female cancer benefit
so this plan is really customizable and
flexible depending on your needs
there are more benefits attached to the
healthplex plan and it is very
affordable
and if you are interested to know more
about healthplex and other health
insurance plans
please contact a manulife insurance
advisor and we will make it easy for you
to find the one that fits your family's
needs
thank you very much kevin for informing
us about health that's in fact i'm
getting a few messages on social media
now
now they were asking that they were
confirming that you were the first
runner-up
semester chinatown correct yes correct
now you're speaking great words for
manulife and it's really interesting as
you can really custom fit this plan
depending on your needs now our audience
they're really
interested in everything that you've
been saying and we have received a few
questions regarding this plan but we
have
one we have time for one question
sure luis i'd be here we go
the question is my dad is relatively
healthy and added protection is great
however he is already a senior citizen
can he still apply for this plan
yeah yeah of course healthplex is
available for customers
from age 0 to 70 years old and they are
covered up to age 100.
so your dad can apply for the healthplex
3ci plus plan
which includes uh elderly and 57
critical nss coverages
aside from cancer heart attack and
stroke wow
the health flex really covers anyone and
everyone in the family
now we would like to spend more time
with kevin and ask more questions
but for now we do have to say thank you
to you kevin all right thank you also
luis and to everyone who listened
uh don't forget to invest in your health
take care and stay safe everyone
thank you very much and of course taking
care of ourselves and being responsible
about our health also means getting a
health plan that will protect us from
sickness
and medical emergency so inaudible once
again kevin to know more about health
flex and many life's other health
products
you can talk to the insurance advisor
who invited you or scan the qr code
flash on your screen and submit your
details so we can assign a manual life
insurance advisor to reach out to you
and for those that already have an
insurance plan with manulife
you can easily manage your policy view
payment information
pay online get e-receipts and more
through manulife
online you may access your manulife
online account by scanning the qr code
shown on our screens there you go
now it is time to introduce our last but
definitely not the least
from our set of speakers she is the
president and medical director of bello
medical group
a celebrated dermatologist and doctor to
the starstone for pioneering the skin
care
laser and liposuction industry in the
philippines please give it up for the
[Music]
beautiful
to all of you manulifers thank you so
much for inviting me in manulife
i'm learning a lot i'm taking notes from
ethol who was my batchmate
classmate and rose who has been a friend
for such a long time thank you for the
plugging
and hi luis i miss you it's about a baby
you talk vicky yes how are you anyway
i'm going to talk about
i think more joyful things i agree with
rose it's about joy
it's not about being happy because
happiness is temporary but joy
radiates from you no matter what the
circumstances are
and what's a good way to keep your joy
of course
it's important to care for yourself or
self-care
you know even when you fly in an
airplane they always tell you make sure
you put your oxygen mask first before
you help someone
i know manulifers are all about helping
people other people
making sure they're going to have money
for their illnesses or whatever
but if you're running on empty if you've
given so much of yourself and you have
nothing left then you can't help them
anymore
so this is going to be about you and how
you can take care of yourself next slide
please
okay so what happened during the
pandemic did it make us more beautiful
i don't think so in spite of the fact
that you're just staying home next slide
please
there is something called the quarantine
15. can anybody guess what this
is it means remember freshman
15 when you're young go to first year
college you're kind of stressed you gain
well a lot of people have gained weight
over the pandemic they can't go to the
gym
they just stay in the house you're
scared to walk out in the streets
so can i show you the cute cartoon next
slide please
yeah that's what i do to scarlet all the
time i pinch her and then i
go like this but 15 pounds is average
weekend
during the pandemic for some people and
of course some people are getting
stressed because they can see the
end of the they can see the light at the
end of the tunnel
because of vaccinations and everything
and then what we're going back to see
everyone we need to get rid of that 15
pounds
next slide how are you going to do it of
course eat a balanced diet you know this
has been something that everybody's been
discussed
discussing for a really really long time
but i don't know many people that do it
right
um especially avoid eating junk food and
sweets because that's what you usually
eat when you're stressed next slide
please
so we have to eat a lot more foods and
vegetables
right i actually am into intermittent
fasting i think it's wonderful
all the new studies a lot of studies
have shown that iaf especially if you
follow david sinclair he's a
scientist from harvard university he
talks about how iaf really helps you
live longer
it affects your epi genome it's all
medical but the point is
it's good not to eat for 16 hours so
normally breakfast is something we can
skip
right so we finish eating at seven in
the evening at least i do and then i
don't eat again until about 12
or 11 30 and that's been able to keep my
weight down in fact i've lost 10 pounds
over
akkovit the covet quarantine next slide
exercise exercise is not just good for
your body it's also good for your mind
for your mood um because it's also
important
to look young not just look young but of
course to move young and i was very
proud i just came from bohol
and i was able to keep up with everyone
and the way they moved
i didn't you know nobody had to help me
so i think it's important that you look
really good next slide please
but when all else fails of course where
do you go on a pa
please i'm just waiting for you here
next slide
there's bellow so let's talk about
bellow and how we pivoted
during the quarantine period so that we
help people take care of themselves
well of course in the clinic if you have
we have this 360 degree liposuction
there's been an uptick in the world
especially in the u.s
for liposuction to get rid of the 15
pound weight fast i always think of
quarantine as
a metamorphosis like you enter a cocoon
and then we will emerge more beautiful
right younger looking and happier at the
end of this quarantine
so this is 360 degree liposuction why do
we call it 360 degrees because at bella
we suction
at all angles you know a lot of people
when you're under general anesthesia
they can only suction the front
but since we do it under tumescent
anesthesia we're just a little high
don't
remember anything but you can stand and
turn then we can do the whole three
c 360 degree lipo next slide
so here's our before and after here's uh
bianca valerio who was a model
gained a lot of weight because of stress
and here she is after
next slide so
i don't know what's happening with this
generation but i see a lot of
big arms with uh women who are 30 and
below i
you know i've been in practice for 31
years i've done
15 000 liposuctions in my life and i've
noticed in the past 10 years for some
reason
people are getting big arms the young
kids and i think it's because of the
food maybe because of
hormones in the food you know so that's
why
for some reason they're getting big arms
so this is maurice said was very
conscious because every time she sang
the microphone the camera would go to
her arms and this is her after
liposuction of the arms
she did this when she was 21 i think
next slide
this is jinky of course she is my um
very loyal patient who's been with me
for 15 years and this is her before
and she did her makeover because she
wanted to look good for the cameras
whenever manny pacquiao would fight
they would focus on the wives and she
felt that the since most of them were
hispanic mexican
they would be a very beautiful and she
wanted to make our country proud and i
think
i think we achieved that together next
slide
okay another phenomena that i see with
this quarantine is a lot of kids
have very dark circles we call them
panda eyes
one is they're always in front of their
gadgets secondly if you rub your eyes a
lot you cause friction and
hyperpigmentation
too for melanin to be attracted to your
to your
around the eye area thirdly when you
sleep late it really
uh increases your cortisol level and
that's one of the signs dark circles
so we can do something about it because
it makes you look very tired even when
you're not tired next slide please
so we have a whole thing called the
bellophi and our models for this were
catriona gray and viola
next slide please so this is
piolo and he's doing the bio neutral
glow for the under eye area
this is very popular in korea by the way
if you've been hearing about
the chanel injection this is what it is
it's
nctf 1459 vitamins minerals peptides
hyaluronic acid
you inject it around the area of the eye
it doesn't hurt because of course we put
green anesthesia
and what it does is it nourishes the eye
gets rid of the dark circles
and makes sure i skin tighter so if you
have
you're beginning to have sagging lids
because of rubbing and tearing the
elastic
fibers around your eyes this is
something good you can do
next slide we also have the bellify kit
so you can go to our
shop.bellomed i i forgot i'm not good at
that
shot.bellamade.com we send you an eye
cream peptides
wonderful eye cream that tightens the
skin decreases darkness
um increases elasticity and gets rid of
fine lines and wrinkles we have the eye
mask now the eyes are
a special focus because if there's one
area that needs a lot of hydration
it's around the eye area so you need a
richer
mask around this area next slide
acne breakouts how many of you had had
mask knees so many people have broken
out including julia i think
three months into the pandemic she
called me up dr
bell i'm freaking out i'm breaking out
well this is because
of wearing a mask just the actual
physical rubbing of the mask against
your skin
causes irritation of your oil follicles
and it causes acne
also when you talk the bacteria instead
of just going out into the atmosphere
bounces back into your face touches and
then you're continually rubbing it
in it's very hard to treat because
you're still wearing the mask and you're
still getting the bacteria
so the best way to avoid this is next
slide please
is it masked knee anti-masking mask it's
using the anti-masking mask so i'm very
proud of this mask it took me a long
time i tried at least
100 masks before i found the right mask
it's made of an incredible material that
doesn't make it
it's very soft no corners so it doesn't
cause friction on your face
it has silver and copper so that these
are natural with
antibacterial elements so any bacteria
that touches the mass
dies so it doesn't just keep going back
to your face next slide
again you can get it at bellow um what
else has happened oh my gosh this is so
great
masks are what people wear when they
have a nose lift
or a rhinoplasty but now since
everybody's on a mass we saw a big big
increase in our rhinoplasties
300 percent plus there's this new um
thread
thread no slip and that's also very
popular next slide
because people can hide so here's
rhinoplasty before and after
you know the typical filipino nose is
wide with a round tip and no bridge
so we have to address those three three
things next slide please
yes you just look a lot of course valve
prides itself in getting natural gnosis
our doctors
um actually sculpt your nose beside your
face to make sure that it
matches your shape of your face because
you before they used to have just
ready-made implants they would put and
you have a spanish nose
chinese eyes and a round face it doesn't
look good
so now we make sure that it looks very
natural
and we sculpt it our doctors are good
sculptors they make your nose
bespoke for you next slide
okay skin care transfer 2021 let's see
what's new in skincare
it's not skin emilisson or skip care
a few years ago it was all about 12
steps
15 steps menopause 20 steps
korean skin care number one i want to
remind
everybody our weather is not at all like
korea it's quite warm in the philippines
and humid so all those serums and oils
on the face
were causing quite a lot of breakout but
now since
we want less we want our products to be
multitasking
in other words next slide please when we
wash our face
we already want the scrub next slide
please
so here is the zeo skip care
so you only have one two three four five
six products including sunscreen already
which you have to use all the time
because our gadgets
do emit some uv radiation which can
cause
a lot of pigmentation even reading
by a bright light that's why i keep
telling them to turn off off my light
when
i'm not on air because it can attract
all the melanin to the skin
like a magnet so this is a skip care
next slide
so we start with water you know like we
took
sunblock exfoliating accelerator there
are two creams that everybody if you ask
me
dr bello if you could only use two
products
what would it be i would necessarily say
it's vitamin c in the morning there's a
minimum minimum y vitamin c in the
morning because
it is an antioxidant and it fights free
radicals
and vitamin c for the face it's just
like vitamin c for your body
it kills those pacman cells from eating
up your protein
of course i would and then in the
evening you use vitamin a or retinoic
acid
because that's been something that can
cure pimples it's anti-aging produces
new collagen and of course
i would those are the two products but
for your eyes you do need a separate
product and then the sun
screen which is i don't think a skin
care but a protection
you need it also no matter even if you
don't go out
next slide oh what's that
hi okay what's that one is that the
sunscreen i hope i can't see
okay next slide now next slide please
okay so this is something that i talked
about last year i've been advocating
microbiome for the longest time so there
shouldn't be an s because microbiome is
already an environment what is
microbiome
microbiome is the environment in your
gut
so you're only as healthy and they used
to say you're only as healthy as what
you eat you are what you eat
but no that's not really true you are
what your microbiome is
it's a whole environment like a whole
country in your gut
and you know the filipinos are notorious
for not having healthy microbiome
this is like 90 of the cells in your
body
bacteria both good and bad and it's been
shown to affect
everything from mood from losing weight
from
you know just being healthy being able
to move if you're not balanced in your
gut
it has the literacy effects of the rest
of your body
why are we not balanced in the
philippines because we take
antibiotics like it's candy we don't
finish our seven days
when we're sick we take three days and i
am better now it's gone we stop
that causes resistance to antibiotics we
tend to take antibiotics even when we
don't need it
so it kills all our bad bacteria yes but
it also kills good bacteria
and so you're totally unbalancing your
microbiome
and i found out that if you just get
healthy microbiome you will lose more
weight
your skin will clear up there's so many
advantages
where do you get it next slide please
michael yan is essential for human
development immunity and nutrition next
slide
okay this is something that i've learned
to eat every day
i think the koreans have good skin a lot
because they
eat kimchi all the time we need
fermented food
that has good bacteria to replenish what
we have lost
i've already got i used to love kimchi
but now
i can't stand it anymore because i'm
eating it every single day
but what i do is i put kimchi with a
like a wrap
like a taco wrap or a lumpia wrapper and
then i put a little chicken that's
broiled
and it really has helped me keep healthy
and made my skin much better next slide
now skin care you are you you are not
like anybody else you are special
so you should really go to your
dermatologist to have
personalized skin care you know a lot of
people come to the clinic i want what
she did i want what she's using
but you know you go to an expert because
they can analyze your skin
and determine what it is that you need
so please listen to your doctor
as rose said stop going to the internet
it's become such a headache for us
because they know so much
information but it's not deep and
sometimes it's a lot of times it's wrong
next slide
next slightly so again z-o why do i keep
putting zero here
here because they know bhaji products
for me are the best in the world
of course we have bellow products but i
i bow to
zayn obachi videos good products that
sign
blue light protection so a lot of people
have
skipped sunscreen because they feel
anyway i'm at home well you can't
because
the blue light in your gadgets your
computer
your eye your phone they do cost damage
to your collagen and elastin
in fact i'll show you a biopsy of that
next slide
um what is it doing to your skin next
slide i think i'll be on time next slide
please
so the new york times talked about what
is
all that screen time doing to your skin
next slide
it emits a blue light which can totally
cause hyperpigmentation
fine lines and wrinkles destroy your
elastin and collagen
next press again and i'll show you a
biopsy of what it looks like
so if you look here those are holes in
your dermis
that are caused by blue light alone no
no sun damage
just blue light damage so you have to
protect yourself what's the best thing
to do is to use sunscreen even if you're
at home
and make sure that it's a broad spectrum
sunscreen next slide that protects you
from uva
b's and c the bella products do protect
you we have a new product that's very
popular was the number one selling
product on sharpie
it's a powder sunscreen so not only do
you get protected
but you also have some light makeup next
slide
mask knee treatments well if all else
fails and your
mastery is really bad you can get some
of these products
at home just go to our shop.developmed
website
these are the zeo oil control pads they
have salicylic acid
and a lot of things that will calm the
skin down so not only is it
antibacterial it's anti-inflammatory and
it normalizes the
shedding of the skin you just put it all
over your face one pad after you wash
your face next slide
vivace vivace finally i'm so happy
because there's a machine that can
control acne and oiliness
i had very bad acne and that's why i
became a dermatologist because nobody
could cure it and i was already 30 and
it was so ugly
and here now with vivace we can actually
dry up the oiliness using this machine
that's also anti-aging so if you see on
your left side
this before with all the acne and look
how small the pores are
how smaller much smaller the face is
and how much clearer it is without the
acne next slide
now we have a lot of home skin care
devices because of the last year
where everybody wanted to stay healthy
and have good skin
at home so here in 15 minutes now but
anyway hurry hurry next slide please
so we have some of our bellow it
yourself kits you call it
the diy as opposed to diy which is do it
yourself
so we have the body scrub a lot of
people still want to look
bright and lighter skin that's great for
you it's a soap
and a scrub and it's perfect really and
an illuminating system it works really
well
and then we have the face brightening
kit of course for some reason for
the philippines is the number one when
it comes to
caring about armpits we want our armpits
beautiful
even tone not dark no no
chicken skin no cracks no no
sagging so the way to do it is with the
armpit perfecting kit next slide
and we have this one this is my favorite
um it's brand new it's only been around
a month
but it's a mask from korea dr
fans mask and this amazing mask next
slide
it's it's so good because it has a micro
electric current micro current next leg
so you put it on your face it's two
sheets
and you have this amazing hydrating
solution that's made of peptides
ceramides hyaluronic acid you put it on
your face there's a wet mask
then you put the you put this thing
which is like the tube
it's like conducting gel and then you
put another mask which has coria
current you don't feel any current don't
worry
but it does drive the solution really
deep into your skin because you need
hydration from
inside out not just on the surface but
you want it to come from inside
out and you will see when you do it your
skin will feel so
soft and hydrated and the next day you
will see a nice lift you can actually
feel that your face is a little hard to
open your mouth because it's so tight
next slide online dermatology we're
doing a lot of zoom consults it's so
great i get to stay home and still meet
all of you
um you do it through you can write again
on our shop.belomet.com next slide
please so
who did i call i think it was julia that
i first consulted and
yeah so i did jess wilson so many people
over the pandemic who were just breaking
out left and right next slide
so it's great i love it because actually
it's face to face more
and um yeah i don't know it's just i
feel more personal for some reason on
the zoom console next slide
well thank you everyone and have a bella
beautiful day
remember to stay joyful and grateful you
know
okay we may have we might have a bit of
a technical difficulty with dr vicky but
dr
vicky will be back in a bit thank you
very much
no no we can hear you dr vicky are you
there
hi i'm here okay we want to say
thank you and uh all these things no
matter how
life gets we must never forget to take
care of ourselves tanner our next guest
who will join dr vikki is one of her
bella babies obviously obviously
she never forgets to take care of
herself let's all welcome the beautiful
talented actress and fitness advocate
miss julia barretto
[Music]
hi julia hello hi everyone
thank you manulife for having me dr
vicky um
thank you very much of course julia for
joining us and we're still with dr vicki
now our audience wants to know what's
your take on the trends regarding health
self-care and wellness right now so i
believe our friends in manulife
they sent you reaction boards maybe see
them
okay we have to check yeah me smiley me
sad face and everything oh hey so what
i'm so happy yes
yes we can see them okay and you get to
explain what's gonna happen is
i'll be saying a specific trend and you
have to show your reactions using our
boards
so uh then explain why your reaction is
that way so are you ready
to vicky and julia yes oh hey the first
one
which is basically a fermented tea full
of probiotics and antioxidants
oh julia um i haven't tried it
okay okay i can't be the judge okay so
uh
doc vicki i see a smiling face yes
well i talked about microbiome and
kombucha is one of those fermented
drinks that does give you microbiome
however i would like to say also that it
gives you gas
and it bloats you a bit so i would still
do kimchi but it's
if it doesn't affect you that way okay
next up this is something that if i had
one
i'd put a big smile on it pimple popping
videos
addicted to it if i was going to be a
dermatologist
it would be because of that it's so
satisfying
it's either you love it or you hate it
yeah dr vicky do you ever get sick of
doing the procedure
or you also feel the relief that the
patient does
no i love doing it i love it the more
creamy
the bigger the more exciting that's what
you call
instant gratification i guess we're all
addicted to it and some are in denial
that they enjoy it
okay next up led facial mask
[Music]
julia smiley i bought not a lot from
online stores
but you know what honestly nothing works
better than an led
mask from your clinic
from your dermatologist's clinic so
don't do it at home but your thoughts on
the led facility
you know i bought it depends right the
led mask that i guess we're talking
about the red light and the blue that's
really good
but i don't know about the home devices
i'm not sure and then there's this new
led mask
that looks like current you know that
when you close the light make that i
think
yeah but it doesn't that one i tried it
it didn't do much
so i'm neutral it it depends i think as
rose said you get what you pay for so if
it's cheap it probably doesn't work
and it's a more expensive kind it will
work
is
but that's our giveaway to the
ambassadors
well hopefully next soon bye you have to
react to
plant-based meat
[Music]
um okay see i don't know i can't see
um
so i guess you're both iffy about it
well i tried it
beyond meat but india gonna satisfy
you know and then it had continued to go
by this vegetables for
a little mind blowing
all right personally i liked it julia
um if there is a substitute
i would try it but i can't say totally
yes because i like meat also so i don't
want to be a hypocrite
um but i've tried a lot of unplanned
based
meat that are really really good okay
yeah the next one i saw this on social
media beer
yoga okay now for those who don't know
beer yoga is a type of yoga that
integrates
beer bottles or even consumption of beer
while doing certain yoga poses
oh i haven't tried that
beer yoga face
i think it doesn't make sense i mean i
you know
one of the reasons you do yoga is what
to stretch
and then i think the breathing is good
for your stomach trying to put beard and
you'll get a beer belly it's
counterproductive i mean and it's a fake
relaxation you want to learn to relax
just by meditating while you're doing
yoga okay
next glass skin facial of course
what's the best part about the glass
skin facial
uh well the best part about it is still
being confident
going out even without makeup and
your skin looking luminous glowing and
very youthful
and being a k like you
youthful glowing and luminous you are
very yes you me
me you
um and as a k drama fan
um they all have glass skin so
i like that it's achievable now
especially in the fellow clinic
all right next up poor vacuum
i tried okay
disappearing again let us knock bellow
about it why the sad face though
because it can be so traumatic on the
face i've tried it just to see what it's
like
um it it has so much pressure when you
suction then you break blood vessels
especially around the nose
so and i think in a way it might
stimulate the oil glands to produce more
oil
i don't i don't think it's a good idea
okay last but not the least that you
have to react upon
intermittent fasting
okay put it to the right place ah okay
so
eight hours they followed the 16-8
protocol what about you guys do you
follow 16-8 or do you go
a bit past it um
me i follow the 16-8 but if i can go
longer i will go
longer doctora yeah
yeah i do 17
i think 17 seven i'm about 17 seven yeah
because i don't eat breakfast so i eat
my last meal is seven
and then my next meal is seven p.m
and my next meal is twelve noon usually
but if i can't take it like eleven
thirty two for the
[Music]
because it stresses your body just right
to wake up your anti-aging epigenomes
maximum so it stresses so you repair
your body while you're
and what i found out everyone manual
manulifers you try it
i've never felt so energetic as when i
do an
iaf you total iafa because for so long
i was making malay i was drinking
vegetable juice
but that's still no calorie but it had
because it had half
an apple which is about 40 calories but
that destroyed the whole fast
so it should really be coffee with no
sugar or
water long then you'll feel like you
know like when you're running i hear you
get a second win
when you're if you feel so strong i'm
i'm
but i'm the less i eat actually the more
energetic i feel well
i'm going down
thank you very much julia in the car to
vicky for a fun and informative bit but
we will see doctor vicky later on
sapping health talk segments so we'll
take a quick break with doc vic and
we'll talk to julia
we'll see you in a bit dr vicky
so julia how are you taking care of
yourself and your whole well-being
during quarantine uh you know what i
really
just tried my best to find ways to keep
myself
sane finding activities that could be
the perfect
outlet for whatever anxiousness anxiety
or worries that i had
are you a yoga person are you a hit
person um what do you follow
okay so i'm the biggest pilates fan okay
yes i like pilates because i think it
hits the muscles that we don't think
we should be hitting and then it's all
sort of like a meditation for me
like um like it's a quiet time it's the
time to breathe and get your stretches
in
but i realized that i also it's not
you can't just be fit and not be strong
so
when i realized that i wanted to feel
more strong
more strong and just more strength
that's when i kind of
mixed it up with like weight lifting and
a lot of um
circuit and a lot of cardio
although i'm not the biggest fan of
cardio we have to for our
stamina i mean i'm not a fan of running
uh that are just last time um
do you mix any other diet with ief like
for example have a friend
who does if and keto ecobot do you eat
anything as long as it falls inside the
window
you know what when i was a few years
back i thought the best diet
is just eating less than what you should
be in taking
but i think the older you get them the
most sustainable and easy to maintain
diet is just
the balanced diet so um i also realized
when i diet
so much so strictly it affects so much
my attitude and
my my patience and everything
so what i've been doing now that's been
working for me is just
um balanced diet just more workout
because i like to eat
so work out and just being active right
now i can eat whatever i want
don't eat and to go aside from working
out
and eating healthy now one thing that
has been resonating with so many people
um throughout this whole webinar is how
we take care of our mental health
now one thing i guess unfortunately it's
part and parcel
of what we do in the industry is the
negativity on social media so how do you
handle all that
well you know it's something that i that
i grew up with
just i lived with criticism my entire
life
i wouldn't say that now i'm immune to it
i don't think it's something you'll ever
be immune to but i think
now i've become wiser and how to handle
it
um so like what i always say it's so
important for you to compartmentalize
things that matter to you and the things
that don't so
you know when it's the criticism from
people i don't know and who don't know
me and don't play a significant
significant role in my life it's easier
to shrug off
and not worry about
i mean the criticism that only matters
to me is of course the people that
are really within my circle and my
family and
you know the people who can be honest
with me and constructive
constructive critics of them indian
criticism
just break it down yes exactly so
compartmentalizing
you're a fitness advocate
again who just want to take that first
step for me
that's the most difficult part is taking
that first step into your fitness
journey what do you want to tell them
well you know i'm also not um
perfect so for example now i was
in lock-in for one month and i was
filming every day
the whole day so it didn't give me much
time to really work out
so tonight actually is going to be my
first time to work out after a month and
day one
is usually what i dread the most because
you don't feel as strong and your
motivation is not the same
but you know what the first step is um
the most
important because you know after you
take the first step
and i mean it's domino effect and it's
the beginning of everything so
take that first step and you'll be
surprised it's going to change
everything for you
don't be afraid thank you very much
your audience will have more good vibes
maybe call on dr join us
hi dr vikki welcome back so we'll have
another game now this game is called
never have i
ever i'm sure julia has seen it in
different vlogs
she's i'm gonna mention a few instances
if you've done it please raise the check
if you haven't then you raise the
x or the cross okay okay so here's the
first one
never have i ever binged an entire
netflix series in one day oh
see julia did already
okay so julia first things first what
series
emily and paris okay elegance
oh yes but you don't have the time
or yeah i feel guilt because scarlett
sleeps with us
so no time to do it no i did emily in
paris in
three days but not sorry because the
questions overnight there but so it was
a big idea so when you have babies
jules you can't do it anymore yes okay
next
up never have i ever gone vegan
i tried hi malet
okay so how was it for you julia oh i
lasted only two to three weeks i think
um meat is very important to me and
because i did like a blood test wherein
you find out
what foods are good for you yeah i'm i'm
tolerant to all types of
of meat so i wanted to keep that in my
diet
all right next up is never have i ever
not eaten and you know a lot of people
are guilty for this
never have i ever not eaten for one
whole day to lose weight
yeah not good though not good now this
was to go to the time now when people
were still
missing for him that that's the only way
how to lose weight they might knock
bella
yes that's actually you slow down your
metabolism when you do that
so it's not a good idea yeah it's really
i have to show you the way to go
controversy never have i
ever gone more than two days without
showering
okay what
me you shower five times a day or three
year whenever i prescribe a shower
heard about duck bella they're saying
that sometimes it a bit maybe too much
because you lose certain oils
and skin well the advice is don't shower
more than two times a day
right and then don't take very hot
showers which i love to do
kailan warm lung because it will dry up
your skin
but i don't listen to my own advice but
i'm telling you that's what you should
do
but me
[Music]
never have i ever stopped an x
in social media
[Laughter]
apparently your reaction is you have
before
what if what if you accidentally
liked his picture oh my god
oh my god no you know i remember
if i did i would scream i guess i but i
think what i did is i used to use my
friend's phone
[Laughter]
we have some questions in a bit but for
everyone it is not too late to hit the q
a box and ask your questions for our
speakers right now we're getting a lot
of questions malasa audience not then
i'm also excited to hear our guests
answer all these but before that make
sure to stay tuned
until the end of the webinar because
manulife philippines is giving away
telemedicine vouchers from med
philippines to 10 lucky winners now
these vouchers can be used to consult
with doctors in the safety
of your own home so please watch out for
that now before we proceed with the q
a or our health talk we'd like to first
acknowledge the presence of our friends
from the media
we have our friends from preview people
asia click the city one in manila
female network abs-cbn manila times
where is ed oy
manila society and of course lifestyle
portal
and now we're ready to bring back all
our guests on screen for our q a segment
hi guys welcome back to miss rose doctor
ed vicki
and yeah we have dr ed with us okay
is uh doc vicki and mom rose with us
yeah i'm not there
well she'll be here okay we'll start
with you so what are the common
illnesses that
we need to watch out for as we continue
to work from home um people hear about
vitamin d
deficiency of obesity anxiety
so what can we do to prevent all that
well vitamin d definitely because you
don't get enough sun
so you should really go out and and you
know at least 10 minutes a day
between the hours of uh before 9 a.m
because the sun is really bad there
anxiety i am such a believer in
meditation so i was so sad when i saw
rose's uh thing that said only five
percent of people meditate
and i think that's really a good way to
to quiet yourself down just really be
still and quiet and then
it get gives you a strength to face the
day
so yeah i would really recommend it i
there's a meditation
thing and it's called the brian weiss
w-e-i-s-s for
manulifers who want to do a good
meditation it's for health
and it's really been helping me i think
stay healthy
well for julia who's also now a fitzpo
people are asking who
is your fit spoke you know what with or
without dr
bello in this call i would have to say
it's her oh
i love you julia ricky it's pretty
amazing i remember
entering her house and she was just in
this robe and i couldn't help but take a
photo and be like oh my gosh i want to
be exactly like her when i grow up
thank you for not saying grow old
no no no all right next question is for
dr
ed dr ed as parents how to deal with
children distressed because of online
school i know it's such a new format
that you know kids are having a hard
time even our teachers are having a hard
time
um because they're at home the
boundaries um there are no more
boundaries the place is
considered as rest it's back to work or
school and of course the lack of social
interaction so how
will parents deal with that first and
foremost it's very important to
have a differentiation between very
young children who may
display distress in a different way
so those who are much much younger
they would be more clingy more anxious
more withdrawn
possibly uh children usually manifest
that they are
in distress when they are more irritable
or agitated or those who have gone
advanced in terms of the things they are
able to control like bad wedding they
may go back
into younger behaviors
so it may be very very important to
reassure
them uh parents need to be
the model for kids as vicky was
mentioning you know we look into like uh
when when there's a crisis in the inside
a plane
we try to look in into the eyes of the
uh steward stewardesses to reassure us
and it's very important as parents that
we reassure
our kids now uh the older kids
luckily are actually digital natives
so they have their gadgets with them
all day actually even when sleeping
uh it's right beside them no so very
important what we could
what parents can do is to make sure that
you
in involve them in decision making
how they would want to restructure their
day
very important as i mentioned earlier
how are you feeling about this
what are the main things that uh causes
problem
problems uh especially with online
schooling and
and all all that um we could also
help them uh this was already
highlighted by
by vicky etc when she uh
highlighted how we can solve problems
also by uh rose uh you
you teach them how to see for example a
negative thing such as what
what's going on right now in a more
positive way in fact
these present as opportunities right now
okay opportunities to to
look into what are the things that i
could learn
over the course of this work from home
or
or online schooling situation but if
everything else fails for example they
have had previews or pre-existing
mental health problems it may be
important to
also involve their respective physicians
in being able to carve out what might be
the
next best thing to do okay thank you
very much
dr ed now miss rose now during your
times mahathir medical
what was the percentage of people using
you know health insurance
or against those that rely mostly but
the common means of financial assistance
like you know health cards
or government benefits okay forty
percent
only forty percent for hmos um
then of course you have the ten percent
of field health that makes it fifty
hmos and corporates would be 40 because
they're one of the same right it's
substitutional
and the rest really 50 are
personal personal payments that's why
i'm a strong advocate of saving
a strong advocate of buying additional
insurance as you get ahead in your
career
as you get older you get promoted
instead of thinking of buying a new
phone why don't you add to your
insurance
health care benefit because you never
know when it's going to come when it's
going to hit you
and you don't want to be in a panic when
you have no choices left
for you anymore and yeah julia let me
ask you
we were talking about it earlier about
the unfortunate um you know part and
parcel of what we do in the industry
now once for example that you're getting
you know a lot of negativity online
does your family play a factor or do
they let you be
oh that's the biggest factor for me i
think that's the most important support
you could get
um and at the end of the day i feel like
when you have
your family as your core support i think
you're you'll be fine
okay my family will always be there to
lift you up
now miss rosh we have a question we have
a they want someone wants to ask about
chemotherapy
if it's still the treatment for cancer
no uh there are three types depending on
your type of
depending on your cancer for example
breast cancer
uh if it's operable they'll do surgery
sometimes they'll put chemotherapy first
right wiki because they want to shrink
the tumors
and then after that they'll do
regeneration therapy so it's not either
or
it's all of the above because that's
just the nature of the
enemy right it's so treacherous and i
speak from personal experience
my daughter who never smoked led such a
healthy life
lifestyle has good genes because we have
no cancer in our family
passed away from lung cancer at the age
of 39 just
a few months ago seven months ago and
it was inexplicable because everything
that we say we should be doing she was
doing she exercised she wasn't
overweight
slept well but you never know because i
think cancer nowadays is also
environmental right it's not
environmental and all the things that we
put in our food all the additives
so it's a combination of if anyone knew
what caused
causes cancer then he'd be a billionaire
right unfortunately it's still an
unknown
yes dr vicky you were you wanted to ask
a question let's try the question
because um
rose just said that she brought her
daughter to sloan gathering
and i was wondering because i hear a lot
about immunotherapy
and that it you know from my
understanding rose it's like
if you have a bacterial infection and
you do culture culture and sensitivity
you put the microbe there and you put
the antibiotics around that will work
best is it true that they can do this
for cancer as well that there are 89
different kinds of breast cancer for
example
so they're different medicines that
could actually attack that but they just
give you
one chemo that will kill carpet bombing
everybody and it's just a question of
whether
the person dies or the cancer dies
depends on your strength but that they
could actually
nowadays be more specific
but because of um big pharma it's a 20
billion dollar industry they don't want
to go there first
i mean i just hear this i think maybe
you have more experience because you
want to so
um chemotherapy now is very targeted
okay it's not a shotgun approach anymore
they actually do dna testing to figure
out whether your dna is compatible with
the chemotherapy they're recommending to
you
but immunotherapy still in the
um developmental stages i was trying to
get my daughter into an immunotherapy
clinical trial but it was only stage one
so they said between the stage one and
the targeted
chemo dr drillon of
sloan kettering was recommending doing
the targeted first and then
when chemotherapy on the second or third
stage unfortunately after i had done
that
i actually coincidentally somebody from
israel got in touch with me by internet
asking me
if i wanted to do some consulting
because i want to penetrate the
philippine market
and they are very high on immunotherapy
but i was
i was just a few months late but no
vicky they have targeted they will check
your
your dna you have to go strong catering
gives you a test
bloody expensive it costs three thousand
dollars but they will map out your
entire
dna is that the same with the
philippines already rose
i said that one is that one oh in the
philippines
for example if you have lung cancer the
first thing you'll do is test if you're
if your es kg positive or an ef's
are positive or negative they're they're
beginning to do it but
they don't have the same options variety
of options as you would let's say in
this
in in the us or in europe but but we're
not far behind you know many of the
doctors were already talking the same
thing
thank you very much uh miss rose um sir
ed my question for you is
um how do you stay mentally healthy
while caring for someone who has
mental issues at the same time it's
sometimes difficult having to be strong
when all you want to do is give up very
very important uh question because i i
know that
a lot of us are caring not just for even
well mentally healthy mentally ill or
physically ill individuals at this point
very important is we're going back to
what i mentioned
earlier and that is self-care uh it is
okay actually to make sure that you
are a-okay you are not go uh
doing any disservice by taking care of
yourself
uh it's important to take breaks for
example if
there are several of you in the family
it's important to
delegate for example and have your uh
care for for yourself time as well
uh you will only be good for for your
loved one if you are whole
as an individual uh biologically
uh psychologically and socially as well
our paradigm constantly is going to be
by a psychosocial
even that individual that you are
helping
wouldn't be a whole as a person
if those who are caring for them
aren't uh actually uh a whole
as themselves so very important is
self-care
before we could actually care even for
us doctors i i think all of us
uh rose having taken care of somebody uh
who had cancer and and passed on all of
us
need to start with making sure we are
in the best of care physically mentally
and socially
okay thank you doc last two questions dr
vicky this is for you
now a few industries are now more aware
to be inclusive
in the fashion industry we see plus
models
joining the club of regular lean models
so how do you encourage women to
appreciate their bodies
but at the same time offer liposuction
well of course it you know we only exist
really for people like me
so the reason i put up bella medical
group is because
i was so insecure because i had really
bad skin and i was fat
and you know when i see people i was i
couldn't look at them in the face
because i thought they look at my bad
skin so
i actually applaud people who are very
self-confident who
who are comfortable with with what they
are by the way louise there's a change
now
in beauty standards for example when i
started it was a lot of people wanted to
be very thin now no they like to be
a little malaman it used to be breasts
for the thing now it's butts
you know so when people say i'm very
comfortable
i go good for you i wish i were like you
but i'm not
so for people who you know sometimes if
you just have one thing i always say
a millimeter scar on the face is a
kilometer scar in the heart
and if you've been bullied like i was
when i was younger being ugly or fat or
whatever and that's why i was adopted
because i was so palate
it really leaves a big mark and you and
i feel that it's improved my life so
much that i'm more confident now i can
talk
on a zoom with 3 000 people watching
because i'm no longer thinking are they
looking at how ugly my skin is
you know but i always do encourage
especially from the beginning with the
color of our skin i'm so happy to say
that there are many many to go to before
when i started practice eighty percent
would ask to be whiter
that was always the thing now fifty
percent are very happy
being morena all they want is even skin
tone not
you know different colors but just one
brown
thing so i i see that that's you know
that's a really positive thing
last one for julia what's your skincare
routine
oh dr bella would know
but when you get home
when you're done with taping you wash
your face right away what are your musts
telegram the non-negotiables
okay well um what are my non-negotiables
well i have these wipes it's called the
antibacterial wipes that are from ponds
that so that's my first
step really like that's how i clean my
skin and then i'll go in with a cleanser
that's very gentle because i have
sensitive skin
and then pads that are full of
salicylic acid and glycolic acid
to reduce acne and then renew all of my
skin
and then i would go in with my sunscreen
because it's very
important okay well thank you very much
now before we leave do we have any final
words
for our viewers we're starting with you
miss rose
or no i was going to say something to
vicky vicky do you still keep a stash of
your chocolates in your
in your clinic
i love going to visit vicky because she
has the nicest chocolates
are you still indulging in that
i think we may have a problem with dr
vicki's connection
okay my parting words is you know health
matters as they
you say health costs don't for one
minute think it's free
you got to be prepared and you got to be
discerning in your choice of doctors
not every doc not all doctors are
created equal
so you have to do your own research
because at the end of the day
your destiny lies in your hands thank
you very much
thank you it's rose ducked
there we go sorry uh yes as i mentioned
earlier
in the in this pandemic what has
happened is
we lost a lot of our controls and the
objective is to rein in control
so that we could uh and that is by being
more resilient
being more open to uh the different
challenges
and see it in a way we call it reframe
it
in such a way that we see uh the
challenges as
in fact opportunities where we could
actually
emerge from this uh even uh
better than we were uh pre pandemic so
hopefully stay resilient all of us
thank you very much dr vicky well i
i'm going to coach scarlett she just did
something for mega magazine
and she said that we should all be
kinder to each other
more loving and help one another and i
think that would really help us to be
outward centered a bit rather than oh my
god this is so bad
so just you can control your mind so
make it a positive and joyful mind
thank you very much julia um well
just many many things my new life thank
you for having me
um and thank you to everybody who joined
us for our webinar looking forward to
the next one
that was very insightful and helpful now
before we wrap up today's webinar it's
time to announce the winners of medgate
philippines telemedicine vouchers
flash on our screen right now we have
our 10
lucky winners
congratulations a manulife
representative will contact you on how
to claim your prize
would like to thank everyone who joined
us this afternoon for taking time and
actively participating
in our program watch out for more
wellness webinars in the future now be
sure to like and follow manulife
philippines
social media pages for the latest
updates now we would like to hear your
feedback
on this afternoon's webinar simply scan
the qr code on screen and answer our
two-minute survey
thank you very much as always it has
been a pleasure hosting for you manulife
i am luis manzano and i leave you with
this
almost everyone can agree that 12v19
pandemic has upturned lives
what you can do is prepare yourself to
return to your normal routine
and think of ways to be better equipped
for whatever health issue might occur
though you might not be able to tell
when and what the next crisis may be
it is always best to be prepared by
planning for the future
and stay safe
[Music]
um
you need a health plan that fits you
better get manulife health flicks
choose from four health bundles to get
coverage for cancer
heart attack stroke and over 100 other
critical illnesses
build it yourself to get just the right
benefits so you can start to make
every day better in your own way
[Music]
find healthy that fits you perfectly ask
your insurance advisor about it
[Applause]
[Music]
wow
[Applause]
come on
[Music]
you